Guide to the James Hazen Hyde Collection of Allegorical Prints of the Four Continents ca. 1500-ca.1900 PR 27
New-York Historical Society
James H. Hyde Collection of Allegorical Prints of the Four Continents
1500-1900
1600-1800
New-York Historical Society
Hyde, James H. (James Hazen), 1876-1959
PR 27
7.9 Linear feet (766 prints and some posters)
The James Hazen Hyde Collection consists of 766 prints and some posters from the 16th-20th centuries, the majority of which relate to the theme of the Four Continents. Other minor themes in the collection include historical, religious and political subjects, with a small folder devoted to material on Benjamin Franklin. There are also a number of playing cards, caricatures, and popular prints from Épinal.
Access to Collection
Collection is open for research; access requires at least 24 hours advance notice.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The Manuscript Department of the New York Historical Society has Hyde's correspondence, diaries and other papers from 1891 to 1940. The Society also owns an oil portrait of Hyde by Theobald Chartran, from 1901.
The Metropolitan Museum and The Brooklyn Museum have prints, drawings (61 in MMA) and decorative objects representing the Four Continents from Hyde. The Cooper Hewitt has original ceramic furniture and other decorative art objects (ca. 130 pieces), as well as Hyde's collection of photographs of personifications of the Four Continents (ca. 4000 pieces). The Library of Congress black and white film negatives of the Cooper Hewitt's photographs, and the National Gallery of Art has a tapestry donated by Hyde.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Provenance
Gift of James Hazen Hyde in 1953 and 1957.
The collection was formed by Hyde in the first half of the 20th century. It appears from a collectors' stamp that appears on all but a few of the prints, that they were at one time housed in the Musee des Art Decoratifs in Paris.
Arrangement Note
The prints have been kept in the original order devised by Hyde. Hyde divided the allegorical prints roughly by nationality and date while making separate portfolios for religious, historical and political prints, as well as prints from Epinal. Frontispieces and playing cards also merited separate portfolios. While Hyde's order was far from consistent, its preservation was desirable for two reasons: for the historic record of one collector's organizational methods, and for ease of access. At some point prior to their entry into the Historical Society, each of the prints was assigned an "Enregistre" number that corresponded to its place in the original green portfolios. These numbers made it possible to determine Hyde's original order (even those whose original portfolios have been lost) and provide an easy method of identification for future researchers.
The prints are also labeled with "JHH" numbers. These numbers are most likely acquisition numbers for Hyde's entire collection since they run into the 7,000s, and are not sequential except for groups of prints that probably were bought together, such as a set of four prints of four continents.
Three prints had "JHH" numbers but no "Enregistre" numbers, so were arbitrarily assigned the "Enregistre" numbers 3001-3003 and placed loose in Box 1. Similarly, 13 prints had "Enregistre" numbers but no "JHH" numbers. These could be placed in their proper order (in Box 5) but for cataloguing purposes had to be assigned the arbitrary "JHH" numbers 10,001-10,013.
Scope and Contents Note
There are 766 prints in the collection, mostly depicting allegories of the Four continents. Artists used various devices to personify the various continents. American was often shown as a stylized Native American woman, surrounded by exotic animals and plants. Africa was shown with lions, elephants and camels. Asia was shown dressed in rich clothing and surrounded by the riches of the east, while Europe was shown as a queen or aristocrat surrounded with the accouterments of the what was perceived as the center of civilized and cultured life.
In addition to the 600 or so purely allegorical prints, there are roughly 23 prints with religious themes, 30 with historical themes, 8 with political themes, 25 or so caricatures, 8 prints depicting Benjamin Franklin as well as a large number of playing cards. Most of these, however, contain at least a small allegorical figure somewhere within the image. The theme of the Four Continents was made popular by the European explorations of the 16th and 17th centuries and continued to appear well into the 20th century, as Hyde's collection attests. He originally collected the prints, as well as objects donated to other museums, with the intent of publishing a book on the personification of the Four Continents in the major and minor arts.
Biographical Note
Philanthropist and francophile James Hazen Hyde was born June 6, 1876 in New York city. He graduated from Harvard in 1898 with honors in French and German. He then entered the Equitable Life Assurance Society, the business that his father Henry Baldwin Hyde founded, and was vice president of the firm from 1899-1905. To set the scene for a ball he hosted in 1905, Hyde hired Stanford White to "transform Sherry's into a counterpart of the French court of Louis XVI at Versailles." The ball, which was at first reported to have cost $200,000, caused a scandal that led to an investigation into the insurance industry, at the end of which Hyde resigned from all of his business concerns and relocated to Versailles where he lived until 1941. While living in France, Hyde compiled an extensive collection of allegorical prints. Hyde was one of the founders of the Alliance Française and was awarded the Grand Cross of the French Legion of Honor. He died of pneumonia in Saratoga Springs in 1959.
Bibliography
The Four Continents: From the Collection of James Hazen Hyde. New York: Cooper Union, 1961.
Honour, Hugh. The European Vision of America.Cleveland: Cleveland Museum of Art, 1975-1977.
Hyde, James Hazen. "The Four Parts of the World as Represented in Old-time Pageants and Ballets." Parts I and II. Apollo (Dec. 1926): 232-238 and 5 (Jan. 1927): 19-27.
Hyde, James Hazen. "L'Iconographie des quatre Parties du Monde dans les Tapisseries." Gazette des Beaux-Arts (Nov. 1924).
Obituary. The New York Times. July 27, 1959.
Parker, Alice L. "Cooper Union Museum for the Arts of Decoration has presented...." Library of Congress Information Bulletin 19 (Dec. 5, 1960): 694.
Who Was Who in America,vol. 3.
Allegories; Symbolism in art; Engravings (prints); Lithographs.; Playing cards; Woodcuts (prints); Portraits.; Africa –- In art; Asia -– In art; Europe -- In art.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 -- Portraits
- Series I: Allegorical, Mixed Nationalities
  - Vue de la Pendule Allegorique (JHH# 4033 / Enregistre# 1200), 1780s (Folder Portfolio 1)
    General note
    18th Century French Etching, soft and hard ground
    Artist: D.P. Printmaker: Publisher:
  - Asia (JHH# 7816 / Enregistre# 1201) (Folder Portfolio 1)
    18th Century Italian Etching
    Artist: Amiconi Printmaker: Joh. Georg Hertel Publisher:
  - L'Amerique/America (JHH# 7820 / Enregistre# 1202) (Folder Portfolio 1)
    19th Century French Lithograph, hand coloring
    Artist: Printmaker: F.C. Wentzel Publisher: Fr. Wentzel
  - Le Descrittioni Universali (JHH# 7821 / Enregistre# 1203) (Folder Portfolio 1)
    17th Century Italian Etching
    Artist: Printmaker: Picini Publisher:
  - [Asia] (JHH# 7824 / Enregistre# 1204) (Folder Portfolio 1)
    Artist: Amiconi Printmaker: Publisher: Joseph Wagner
  - [America] (JHH# 7825 / Enregistre# 1205) (Folder Portfolio 1)
  - [Africa] (JHH# 7826 / Enregistre# 1206) (Folder Portfolio 1)
  - Les Cinq Parties du Monde (JHH# 7827 / Enregistre# 1207) (Folder Portfolio 1)
    19th Century French Lithograph
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: Codoni
  - Chasse a L'Ours (JHH# 7828 / Enregistre# 1208) (Folder Portfolio 1)
    17th Century French Etching
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: Jean Baptists Bonnart
  - Chasse au Lion (JHH# 7829 / Enregistre# 1209) (Folder Portfolio 1)
  - Chasse a L'Autriche (JHH# 7830 / Enregistre# 1210) (Folder Portfolio 1)
  - Traitte [sic] de Paix 1783 (JHH# 1354 / Enregistre# 3001) (Folder Portfolio 1-A)
    18th Century French Etching, hand coloring
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher:
  - [Africa] (JHH# 6246 / Enregistre# 3002) (Folder Portfolio 1-A)
    18th Century German Etching
    Artist: V. Jasper Printmaker: Publisher:
  - Trachtenbuch (JHH# 6358 / Enregistre# 3003), 1581 (Folder Portfolio 1-A)
    16th Century Dutch Etching
    Artist: Printmaker: Abraham de Bruijn Publisher: Abraham de Bruijn
- Series II: Oversize prints (allegorical, mixed nationalities)
  - Les Differentes Nations de L'Amerique (JHH# 172 / Enregistre# 1211), 1720 (Folder Portfolio 2)
    18th Century French Etching
    Artist: Charles Le Brun Printmaker: Louis Surugue Publisher: Berault
  - La America (JHH# 180 / Enregistre# 1212) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: Dopter
  - L'Amerique (JHH# 308 / Enregistre# 1213) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    19th Century French Stipple
    Artist: Bertrand Printmaker: Publisher: Aumont
  - L'Amerique (JHH# 319 / Enregistre# 1214) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    19th Century French Stipple, hand coloring
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: Clericetti
  - [America] (JHH# 2043 / Enregistre# 1216) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    19th Century French? Etching, hand coloring
  - [America] (JHH# 2044 / Enregistre# 1217) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    19th Century French Etching, hand coloring
  - [America] (JHH# 2045 / Enregistre# 1218) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - [America] (JHH# 2046 / Enregistre# 1219) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Femme Patagonne (JHH# 2104 / Enregistre# 1220) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    19th Century French Soft and hard ground etching, hand coloring
    Artist: J. Grasset Printmaker: J. Laroque Publisher: St. Sauveur
  - Homme Patagon (JHH# 2105 / Enregistre# 1221) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Chef des Patagons (JHH# 2106 / Enregistre# 1222) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Sauvagesse de la Terre de Feu (JHH# 2107 / Enregistre# 1223) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Pretre Medecin de la Terre de Feu (JHH# 2108 / Enregistre# 1224) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Sauvage de la Terre de Feu (JHH# 2109 / Enregistre# 1225) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Homme de Nootka (JHH# 2110 / Enregistre# 1226) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Femme de Lysle de Nootka (JHH# 2111 / Enregistre# 1227) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Guerrier de Nootka (JHH# 2112 / Enregistre# 1228) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Fille de Nootka (JHH# 2113 / Enregistre# 1229) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Nobles Moderne et Ancien du Perou (JHH# 2120 / Enregistre# 1230) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    Artist: Labrousse Printmaker: Publisher: St. Sauveur
  - Femmes Nobles Peruviennes. Moderne et Ancienne. (JHH# 2121 / Enregistre# 1231) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Guerriers Peruviens, Ancien et Moderne (JHH# 2122 / Enregistre# 1232) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Ancien Pretre Peruvien (JHH# 2123 / Enregistre# 1233) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Paysannes du Perou (JHH# 2124 / Enregistre# 1234) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Paysans Peruviens (JHH# 2125 / Enregistre# 1235) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Topilzin de L'ancien Mexique (JHH# 2126 / Enregistre# 1236) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Guerrier de l'ancien Mexique (JHH# 2127 / Enregistre# 1237) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Esclave du Mexique (JHH# 2128 / Enregistre# 1238) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Mulatre Libre du Mexique (JHH# 2129 / Enregistre# 1239) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Esclave du Mexique (JHH# 2130 / Enregistre# 1240) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Montagnard du Mexique (JHH# 2131 / Enregistre# 1241) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Convention entre la Republique Francaise… (JHH# 3734 / Enregistre# 1242) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    Artist: Franc. Piranesi and Jo Barberi Printmaker: Beauble Fils Publisher: Calcographie Piranesi
  - Deer Hunt (JHH# 5370 / Enregistre# 1243) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    Artist: V. Adam Printmaker: Publisher:
  - Tiger Hunt (JHH# 5371 / Enregistre# 1244) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Lion Hunt (JHH# 5372 / Enregistre# 1245) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Rhinoceros Hunt (JHH# 5373 / Enregistre# 1246) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Buffalo Hunt (JHH# 5374 / Enregistre# 1247) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - Vulture attack (JHH# 5375 / Enregistre# 1248) (Folder Portfolio 2)
  - De Waereld (JHH# 5551 / Enregistre# 1249), 1776-1795 (Folder Portfolio 2)
    18th Century Dutch Engraving
  - America (JHH# 6441 / Enregistre# 1250) (Folder Portfolio 2)
    19th Century Italian? Lithograph
  - [Allegories of countries, seasons, etc.] (JHH# 521 / Enregistre# 1251), ca. 1800 (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    17-18th Century German Etching
    Artist: Johann Christoph Weigel Printmaker: Publisher:
  - America (JHH# 6536 / Enregistre# 1256) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    Artist: Gottfried Eichler Printmaker: I. Wachsmuth Publisher: Johann Georg Hertel
  - The Oracle (JHH# 322 / Enregistre# 1257), 1776 (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    18th Century English mezzotint
    Artist: J. Dixon Printmaker: J. Dixon Publisher: R. Sayer and J. Bennett
  - L'intrepide Tristan dans les champs (JHH# 337 / Enregistre# 1258) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    Artist: Trigaul de Beaumont Printmaker: Trigaul de Beaumont Publisher: Gayant
  - America (JHH# 346 / Enregistre# 1259), 1781 (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    18th Century English Mezzotint
    Artist: R.E. Pine Printmaker: Joseph Strutt Publisher: R.E. Pine
  - Jeu Instructif des Peuples (JHH# 745 / Enregistre# 1260) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    19th Century French Etching
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: Basset
  - Europa (JHH# 1116 / Enregistre# 1261) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    18th Century German Etching, stipple, hand coloring
    Artist: Gottfrid Bernhard Goetz Printmaker: Balthasar Sigmund Setlezky Publisher: Johann Christian Leopold
  - Asia (JHH# 1117 / Enregistre# 1262) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - Africa (JHH# 1118 / Enregistre# 1263) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - America (JHH# 1119 / Enregistre# 1264) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - Navis Institoris (JHH# 1369 / Enregistre# 1267) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    19th Century Spanish Etching, hand coloring
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: L. Hondhare
  - Europa (JHH# 1460 / Enregistre# 1268) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    18th Century German Mezzotint
    Artist: Joseph Hartman Printmaker: Christian and Philipp Sebastian Rugendas Publisher: Christian and Philipp Sebastian Rugendas
  - Asia (JHH# 1461 / Enregistre# 1269) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - Africa (JHH# 1462 / Enregistre# 1270) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - America (JHH# 1463 / Enregistre# 1271) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - Europe (JHH# 1516 / Enregistre# 1272) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    Artist: Printmaker: Gosselin Publisher: Gadola
  - Asie (JHH# 1517 / Enregistre# 1273) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - Afrique (JHH# 1518 / Enregistre# 1274) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - Amerique (JHH# 1519 / Enregistre# 1275) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - Oceanie (JHH# 1520 / Enregistre# 1276) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - Peace of Ghent 1814 and Triumph of America (JHH# 1599 / Enregistre# 1277) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    19th Century American Lithograph
    Artist: Mme. Plantou Printmaker: Philibert Louis Debucourt Publisher:
  - L'Europe (JHH# 1600 / Enregistre# 1278) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
    Artist: Gill Printmaker: L. Turgis Publisher: L. Turgis
  - L'Asie (JHH# 1601 / Enregistre# 1279) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - L'Afrique (JHH# 1602 / Enregistre# 1280) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - L'Afrique (JHH# 1603 / Enregistre# 1281) (Folder Portfolio 3A)
  - Europa (JHH# 1702 / Enregistre# 1282) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    19th Century French/German? Etching, hand coloring
  - Asia (JHH# 1703 / Enregistre# 1283) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - Civil Liberty (JHH# 2007 / Enregistre# 1284), 1797 (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    18th Century English Engraving, stipple, etching
    Artist: T. Stothard Printmaker: R. Pollard Publisher: R. Pollard
  - L'Amerique (JHH# 2666 / Enregistre# 1285) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    Artist: Mondon Printmaker: Publisher: Crepy
  - L'Asie (JHH# 2667 / Enregistre# 1286) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - Le Commerce (JHH# 2961 / Enregistre# 1287), 1791 (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    Artist: Charles Lemonnier Printmaker: J. Charles Levasseur Publisher: C. Bloquel
  - [Europe] (JHH# 3427 / Enregistre# 1288) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    20th Century French Photomechanical reproduction
    Artist: Emile Beaume Printmaker: Publisher: Fernand Nathan
  - [Asia] (JHH# 3428 / Enregistre# 1289) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - [Africa] (JHH# 3429 / Enregistre# 1290) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - [American] (JHH# 3430 / Enregistre# 1291) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - L'Europe (JHH# 4032 / Enregistre# 1293) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: Mondhare Mondhare
  - Europa (JHH# 4040 / Enregistre# 1294) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    Artist: Napoléon Thomas Printmaker: Gosselin Publisher: Gadola
  - Asia (JHH# 4041 / Enregistre# 1295) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - Africa (JHH# 4042 / Enregistre# 1296) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - America (JHH# 4043 / Enregistre# 1297) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - Africa (JHH# 5468 / Enregistre# 1298) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    18th Century English? Etching, hand coloring
  - America (JHH# 5469 / Enregistre# 1299) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - Europa (JHH# 6135 / Enregistre# 1300) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    19th Century German Lithograph
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: S. Lipschitz
  - Amerika (JHH# 6136 / Enregistre# 1301) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - Asia (JHH# 6399 / Enregistre# 1303) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    19th Century English Lithograph, hand coloring
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: Thomas Kelly
  - Africa (JHH# 6400 / Enregistre# 1304) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - L'Amerique (JHH# 6450 / Enregistre# 1305) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    Artist: Printmaker: H. Jannin Publisher: Agustoni
  - Capitale de l'Empire de Turcs (JHH# 7379 / Enregistre# 1307) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    18th? Century French Etching, hand coloring
  - Asia (JHH# 7832 / Enregistre# 1308) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    17th Century German Etching
    Artist: Printmaker: Albrecht Schmidt Publisher:
  - Europa (JHH# 7833 / Enregistre# 1309) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    Artist: Albrecht Schmidt Printmaker: Publisher:
  - Africa (JHH# 7834 / Enregistre# 1310) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - America (JHH# 7835 / Enregistre# 1311) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
  - Mercurius (JHH# 7837 / Enregistre# 1312) (Folder Portfolio 3B)
    Artist: Paul Decker Printmaker: Philipp Andreas Kilian Publisher: Martin Engelbrecht
- Series III: Allegorical, French and Irish
  - Tableau Chronologiques (JHH# 321 / Enregistre# 1313) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    Artist: Desimencourt Printmaker: Publisher: Bulla
  - Qui vole trop haut se perd les ailea (JHH# 342 / Enregistre# 1314) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
  - L'Importation Francaise en 1842 (JHH# 3670 / Enregistre# 1316), 1843? (Folder Portfolio 4A)
  - Europe au tombeau de Florean (JHH# 4094 / Enregistre# 1317) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    19th Century French Etching and aquatint
    Artist: F. Oberlin Printmaker: I. Girtin; I.C. Stadler Publisher:
  - Folies du Sciecle [sic] (JHH# 6244 / Enregistre# 1318) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    Artist: H.V. Printmaker: Benard Publisher:
  - L'Amerique et ses Enfants (JHH# 6454 / Enregistre# 1319) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    Artist: Cham Printmaker: Destouches Publisher: Martinet
- Series IV: Caricatures, Irish
  - Subscribe for Bond Certificates (JHH# 2171 / Enregistre# 1320), 1918? (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    20th Century Irish Photomechanical reproduction
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: Allied Printing
  - Emprunt Francais 5% 1920 (JHH# 2172 / Enregistre# 1321.1) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    Artist: Jonas Printmaker: Publisher: Joseph-Charles
  - Emprunt Francais 5% 1920 (JHH# 2172 / Enregistre# 1321.2) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
- Series V: Allegorical and Historical, American
  - For Delaplaine's Repository (JHH# 310 / Enregistre# 1322) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    19th Century English Engraving
    Artist: Birch Printmaker: Lawson Publisher: Rogers and Esler
  - [Uncle Sam confronts the German Butcher] (JHH# 2001 / Enregistre# 1323), WWI (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    20th Century Dutch Photomechanical reproduction
    Artist: Louis Raemaekers Printmaker: Raemaekers, Louis, 1869-1956 Publisher:
  - [Uncle Sam confronts the German Butcher] (JHH# 2002 / Enregistre# 1324), WWI (Folder Portfolio 4A)
  - Triunfo de la Independencia Americana (JHH# 4219 / Enregistre# 1328), 1825 (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    19th Century Mexican Etching, aquatint
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: R. Ackermann
  - L'Afrique (JHH# 6537 / Enregistre# 1329) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
    19th Century French Aquatint
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: Boulard
  - L'Amerique (JHH# 6538 / Enregistre# 1330) (Folder Portfolio 4A)
- Series VI: Caricatures, American and English
  - The European Race (JHH# 174 / Enregistre# 1331), 1738 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    18th Century English Etching
    Artist: Iu. Toner Printmaker: C. Mosley Publisher:
  - European Race for a Distance (JHH# 175 / Enregistre# 1332), 1740 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: Ernon Printmaker: C. Mosley Publisher:
  - The Junto in a Bowl Dish (JHH# 290 / Enregistre# 1333), 1766 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: W. Humphrey
  - The Times, Anno 1783 (JHH# 291 / Enregistre# 1334) (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    18th Century English Etching, hand coloring
    Artist: [Gillray] Printmaker: [Gillray] Publisher: W. Humphrey
  - Britain's Rights maintaind [sic] (JHH# 292 / Enregistre# 1335), 1755 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: L. Boitard Printmaker: Publisher:
  - British Resentment (JHH# 293 / Enregistre# 1336), 1755 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: L. Boitard Printmaker: J. June Publisher: J. Bowles
  - The Balance of Power (JHH# 294 / Enregistre# 1337), 1781 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: RS Printmaker: Publisher: R. Wilkinson
  - The American Rattle Snake (JHH# 330 / Enregistre# 1338), 1782 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
  - Les Grandes Menaces du Commerce (JHH# 347 / Enregistre# 1339) (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    18th Century French etching, hand coloring
    Artist: Tavenard Printmaker: Publisher: Tavenard
  - Poor old England endeavouring to reclaim her wicked AmericanChildren (JHH# 1098 / Enregistre# 1340), 1777 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: Printmaker: [Darly] Publisher: M. Darly
  - Property Protected a la Francoise (JHH# 1701 / Enregistre# 1341), 1798 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    18th Century English Etching with hand coloring
    Artist: Printmaker: [?Ansell] Publisher: S.W. Fores
  - America (JHH# 2576 / Enregistre# 1342), 1778 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: Printmaker: Publisher: M. Darly
  - Britain (JHH# 2577 / Enregistre# 1343), 1778 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
  - Bunkers Hill (JHH# 2578 / Enregistre# 1344), 1776 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
  - The Bull Overdrove (JHH# 2579 / Enregistre# 1345) (Folder Portfolio 4B)
  - The Yankey Torpedo (JHH# 3683 / Enregistre# 1346), 1813 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    19th Century English Etching, hand coloring
    Artist: E--- Printmaker: Publisher: Thomas Tegg
  - The Commissioners (JHH# 3685 / Enregistre# 1348), 1778 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: M. Darly Printmaker: M. Darly Publisher: M. Darly
  - National Opinions on Bononaparte [sic] (JHH# 4215 / Enregistre# 1350), 1808 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: Woodward Printmaker: C.W. [Williams] Publisher: Thomas Tegg
  - John Bull Triumphant (JHH# 4216 / Enregistre# 1351), 1780 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
  - The European Race (JHH# 5677 / Enregistre# 1352), 1739 (Folder Portfolio 4B)
    Artist: Printmaker: C. Mosley Publisher:
- Series VII: Allegorical, American and English